Finding aid to the Ellen Shumsky papers SSC.MS.00493
Sophia Smith Collection
Ellen Shumsky papers
1969-1972
Sophia Smith Collection
Shumsky, Ellen
SSC.MS.00493
0.5 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was recieved from Ellen Shumsky in October 2003. The accession number associated with this collection is 03S-76.
Accruals
Periodic accruals to collection are expected.
Biographical Note
Ellen Shumsky earned her B.A. from Brooklyn College in 1961, her MLS from the Pratt Institute in 1964, and her MSW in psychoanalytic psychotherapy from SUNY at Stonybrook, NY in 1996. In 1969, she joined the newly formed Gay Liberation Front and also co-founded Radicalesbians; in 1970 she co-authored Woman-Identified Woman, which articulated the Radicalesbian philosophy. She was a member of the first radical lesbian consciousness raising group, and helped coordinate additional CR groups. From 1960 to 1980, Shumsky, whose photographs have been published widely in books and magazines, worked as a photojournalist, documenting the gay, feminist, and counter-cultural movements. She was the principal photographer for the gay liberation front newspaper, Come Out, and also published "Women's Songs From the Balkans" in Traditions magazine and "Transforming Ties That Bind: Lesbians, Lovers and Chosen Family" in the journal Psychoanalysis and Psychotherapy (1966).
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Existence and Location of Originals
This collection includes photocopies of original photographs which remain in Ellen Shumsky's possession.
Scope and Contents
Writings about lesbian and feminist issues by Shumsky and others; fliers; minutes of meetings of Radical Lesbians (NYC); other printed materials; photographs (photocopies); and 7 issues of the newspaper, Come Out. The photographs are identified and provide excellent documentation of women together - working, relaxing, marching, etc., and the written and printed materials offer a very good record of aspects of radical gay and lesbian political activism.
Gay liberation movement--History--20th century--Sources; Gay rights--History--20th century--Sources; Lesbians--United States--History--20th century--Photographs; Lesbian feminism--United States--History--Sources; Feminism--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Essays; clippings; Minutes; Typescripts; Fliers; photographs; Shumsky, Ellen; Radicalesbians
- "Come Out: a Liberation Forum for the Gay Community", 1970-1972; 7 items (Box 1)
- Consciousness Raising Group Session "Coming Out", approximately 1970 (Box 2)
- Consciousness Raising Group Session "Why We Do or Don't Go to the Bars", 1970 November (Box 2)
- Radicalesbians meeting notes, approximately 1970 (Box 2)
- "The Woman Identified Woman" drafts and final version, 1970 (Box 2)
- Photocopies of snapshots, approximately 1970 (Box 2)
- Radicalesbians flyers, articles and correspondence, 1970 (Box 2)
- "Lesbians and the Health Care System" Radicalesbians Health Collective, 1970 (Box 2)
- Flyers and Open Letters, 1970-1972 (Box 2)
- "Lesbians as Women", "Lesbians as Women Part II" and "Lesbians as Bogeywomen", Approximately 1970; Grahn, Judy, 1940- (Box 2)